hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference live stream number 54.0
we're discussing mathematical
foundations for a compositional account
of the Bayesian brain
welcome to the active Institute
we're a participatory online Institute
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded archived and
published live stream so please provide
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspective are
welcome
and we'll follow a video etiquette for
live stream
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about getting involved in
live streams and in a variety of other
projects and learning groups
all right well we're in stream number
54.0 and we're going to be learning and
discussing the paper that was submitted
on the 23rd of December 2022 as part of
a dissertation work
mathematical foundations for a
compositional account of the Bayesian
brain by Toby Saint Claire Smith
the video is an introduction for some of
the ideas in this multi-hundred page
thesis it's not a review or a final word
or a thesis dissertation committee
4.0 given the the scope and the
complexity but also accessibility of the
ideas we're going to be approaching it
in a familiar way but also with some
twists
we're going to begin with some
introductions the aims and claims
abstract and roadmap as usual
then we're going to approach the
keywords and the context in a slightly
different way than we've done in a lot
of other
dot zeros and then we're going to kind
of bookend the dissertation and focus
most on chapter one and chapter 7 the
first and the final chapter and chapters
two through six we're looking forward to
unpacking more with Toby in the coming
weeks so we'll begin with some
introductions and warm-ups we could all
just say hello and something that was
exciting for us about the paper slash
dissertation or what brought us to
um the work I'll begin I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in California and I have to
say that six months ago when we started
this journey ha on the heels of the
dissertation being posted when along
with Ali and Dean and others we
decided to embark on this weekly
learning quest uh I was very unfamiliar
with category Theory and thankfully
after closing the window it all escapes
my mind so it's been quite a six month
period to learn and to forget so much
I'll pass to Dean
thanks dally I'm Dean I'm here in
Calgary I think the thing
for me uh when it was first broached the
idea of taking this up
um
about a decade ago I started just
scratching the surface of of this idea
called category Theory and um to see
this amount of work uh put together to
sort of bring a whole bunch of ideas
together
um and as Daniel already mentioned make
it somewhat accessible or I don't know
if it's a beginner's guide or a category
theory for dummies exactly because
there's still a lot in here but in terms
of
um giving us an opportunity to get some
verifications or for me at least that's
what I got with some validations and
some verifications was really helpful so
I am excited about having a chance to
talk about this
and bring the author on eventually and
have that conversation get extended and
I'll pass it over to Ali
thank you
um I'm Ali I'm an independent researcher
from Iran uh well I also had just a
passing Community with a category Theory
and
uh wasn't familiar at all with lots of
terminology and formalism in this thesis
but after uh covering the whole thesis
in our six-month period uh it now begins
uh to make much more sense uh I mean I I
definitely started seeing category
theory in almost everywhere both in
sciences and in also in some other uh
not specifically scientific areas so I'm
really excited to
have these discussions with Toby and
learn even a lot more thanks
excellent
all right on we go
we'll begin here with a meta prompt so
for all of you human and non-human
language models please
fill your context window with this meta
prompt
on to the big questions so we have some
hidden questions that are in white font
below that those who go to the slides
will find and discover but we raised
many questions and uh
Dean early what's just a question that
strikes you today what what is uh a
question that would lead someone to come
to this dissertation
and we're going to be covering a lot of
Toby's summaries in terms of the
contributions Ames claims and Foci of
the dissertation but what what is this
dissertation ask or what would somebody
ask to get to this dissertation
yeah please Dean
I think the first thing for me was if we
are pattern Seekers and and pattern
pattern employers then if you're gonna
look at what the formalism behind that
is then this is a good place to start if
you want to know why we tend to put
things into groups
why things have have a world where
there's something that's in a category
or outside of a category and most
importantly where are the things that
aren't in either of those two places
this gives you some of the operational
backbone to be able to start figuring
that out
awesome
all right on we go
aims and claims of the paper so paper uh
or dissertation draft mathematical
foundations for a compositional account
of the Bayesian brain was uploaded in
late December 2022.
and just uh several overview claims of
the work
our main aim in this thesis is to
formalize predictive coding
through functorial semantics
and Bayesian lenses will provide an
important part of the syntax of
statistical models that we need
in this 54.0 video we're only going to
cover chapter 1 and chapter 7 and we're
going to review them for some really
interesting bold and ambitious claims
and there's a few great overview claims
for the entire work that do a great job
of just distilling down so many hundreds
of pages and so many technical
contributions from page seven the main
individual contribution of this thesis
is
the introduction of Bayesian lenses and
the proof that Bayesian lenses compose
optically and the first sentence of the
abstract this dissertation reports some
first steps towards a compositional
account of active inference and the
Bayesian brain anything else to add on
aims and claims
okay
um either of you please start with the
first half of the abstract
oh
yeah the dissertation reports some first
steps towards compositional count of
active inference and the Bayesian brain
specifically we use the tools of
contemporary applied category Theory
to supply puncturio semantics for
approximate inference to do so we Define
on the syntactic side
the new notion of Bayesian lenses I
think it's important to get the plural
layer and show that Bayesian updating
composes according to the compositional
lens pattern
using Bayesian lenses and inspired by
compositional Game Theory
we Define categories of statistical
games and use them
classify various problems of statistical
inference on the semantic side we
present a new formalization of General
open dynamical systems particularly
deterministic stochastic and random and
discrete and continuous time
as certain co-algebras or polynomial
functors which we show collect into
monoidal open text categories or
alternatively into algebras for
multi-categories of generalized
polynomial functors we use these open
text
categories to Define monoidal
bi-categories of cilia
dynamical systems which control lenses
and which Supply d-target or our
puncturial semantics just one quick
thing
if you're like me you had to spend a lot
of time finding out what do these words
actually mean
we're going to come to talk more about
words all these words
and Ali second half the abstract
accordingly we construct functors which
explain the bi-directional compositional
structure of predictive coding neural
circuits under the free energy principle
thereby giving a formal mathematical
underpinning to The bi-directionality
observed in the cortex along the way we
explain how to compose rate coded neural
circuits using an algebra for a
multi-category of linear circuit
diagrams showing subsequently that this
is subsumed by lenses and polynomial
functors
because category theory is unfamiliar to
many computational neuroscientists and
cognitive scientists we have made a
particular effort to give clear detailed
and approachable expositions of all the
category theoretic structures and
results of which we make use
we hope that this dissertation will
prove helpful in establishing a new
well-typed science of life and mind and
in facilitating interdisciplinary
communication
awesome okay
here's the road map
we're only showing a zoomed out view
because if the other papers we've
discussed were going on a road trip this
is the uh continent scale road trip
um the dissertation is 230 plus pages
long it's in seven chapters that are
shown here
and in 54.0 we're going to be focusing
on chapter one and chapter 7. so it's
quite
a piece of work
and this is just the background and
context there's a table of contents with
more information and on what the
chapters do
let's take a few more steps or moments
in the background and context to really
set up the reading and expressing of
this work and really this kind of work
so thanks a lot to Jr for preparing some
of the following slides
here we have some
selections from several Works in
mathematics and category theory on
reading math
there's a real joy in doing mathematics
we've all heard it before but it really
comes to be true when we enact it that
way
um
the challenge of mathematical
understanding is to find a way to make
new mental images in oneself on the
basis of formal definitions to make
these definitions intuitive to feel what
they are talking about
and
um Jr's summary of some of the uh ways
that math is utilized in this
dissertation so
in regards to the writing in this thesis
just like with anything else something
is being written for an audience Toby is
writing to an audience of domain experts
and a dissertation committee ultimately
to demonstrate and embed new
contributions to knowledge he also takes
a pedagogical approach a teaching
approach and Jr asked is this
pedagogical approach something you see
in most PhD Theses briefly
I would suggest no
and on the reading of this thesis it
helps to be clear why we're reading it
if to help understand or sense make
active inference models then aim to read
it at one level and take the rest on
faith
if we want to understand the formality
better of the really nitty-gritty
category Theory itself then read to that
level and go deeper
any thoughts either of you fellows on
the first reading math slide
okay and on the second reading math
slide
a few more great tips on just reading
math and what we're doing with math so
first eyes on the prize math is a
language and as such it's there to
convey something about the world
about the structure of this thesis
overall and overwhelmingly there is a
plain English exposition of what
concepts are needed and why with nice
transitions foreshadowing and back
references there's also a true wealth of
beautiful diagrams which in category
Theory have a formality that those used
to schema type diagrams will be
pleasantly surprised by
they're definitely challenging to
interpret it is a new visual language
for some however it's one that can be
admired without necessarily needing all
the formality
about roles
of definitions in reading of math
what the audience knows is truth is a
shared prior belief things start from
there
these definitions are used to build up
further truths through logic and the
proofs and from the bessis citation in a
mathematical text the most important
passages are neither proofs nor theorems
they are definitions mathematical
language works as a construction game
where words are truly defined that is
constructed from other words that
themselves have been previously defined
and about role of proofs in Reading
maths very similar to providing
well-argued evidence in any technical
writing
um math is technical writing with math
as its particular structure and there's
other great things to read but that's
all all mentioned here
just at an overview are there any other
thoughts that either of you would add
just about reading math or reading this
kind of technical work which can be
[Music]
um
like getting dropped in the deep end I
mean we're getting dropped into The
Cutting Edge
PhD contribution Frontier of knowledge
so how do we negotiate that especially
when there are these esoteric or
inscrutable symbolic systems that
seemingly constitute the majority of the
words in certain passages Dean
I think this is May might be a slightly
strange metaphor but what I would equate
this process to as a reader I would
equate it to being offered to build a
ten thousand piece puzzle except you
have to build it backwards so you're you
don't actually have the benefit of
having image and contrast at first all
you basically have is the geometry but
when all the pieces fit together you're
then allowed to flip it over so you have
to be really committed and I I
my hat is often uh to the work that Toby
has done because for him to make it
coherent given the actual volume of
information that he would like to pass
along
um
part of my grinding through this was the
thought in my head that if I'm grinding
through this I can't imagine what the
author had to go through so even if
you're excited about this it's it's
still a huge commitment so
it's so true Ollie anything
uh just wanted to add that uh well uh
obviously category theory is
um very abstract
discipline even for mathematicians so I
agree with Dean that uh doing such a I
mean such an admirable task of
um I mean organizing the materials of
the dissertation in such a coherent way
as a truly a Hercule Herculean task to
do so uh but another point is that well
I mean even in the realm of category
Theory most of the things uh done so far
uh is done in the purely mathematical
world so uh and applying those concepts
of carry a category theoretical Concepts
to uh some Realms outside of mathematics
is something that's just been explored
for uh the last uh few years at least
seriously so
um
I believe Toby didn't have much to start
with
given that the scarcity of material in
the applied category Theory area but of
course uh it's a burgeoning field and
it's
gaining attraction quite rapidly so I
hope to see much uh interesting works in
the future
um and I believe Toby's dissertation
will help a lot in shaping the future
trajectories
great comments about applied category
Theory
onto the keywords so three big keywords
are category Theory
Bayesian brain and active inference
and then category theory is really a
language of its own
uh for some of the relevant keywords
that we pulled out
in our shared epistemic Niche decoded
document that we utilized to collaborate
over the last last uh six months as a
team
we uh here's some of the terms that we
had on the right side and we had a full
table that people who go to the slides
or the coda document can explore more
but there were so many creative words
just words that you're not gonna get
outside of Applied or basic category
Theory it was uh quite a Learning
Journey just from a lexical perspective
so a lot of keywords and a lot of domain
specific words
in category Theory but we keep the
bigger picture in mind about Bayesian
brain and active inference
and one last piece of information here
before we head off into the dissertation
itself Jr during their internship over
the last several months at the Active
inference Institute among other works
completed an absolutely
beautiful syllabus Adventure Mode
syllabus for introduction to category
Theory applied to octave inference and
it's hosted on our GitHub at The
Institute so hopefully people can find
it useful and continue to version and
utilize it and make contributions to it
I'll just read the summary
it's for any curious thrill-seeking
active inference Institute participant
who wishes to study and conduct further
research on active inference related
papers that involve category theoretic
tools and we have a fractal embedding of
a quotation from Christopher white on
model stream number 1.1 we have a finite
time on this earth right and a finite
time to dedicate to learning things
the syllabus is centered around the joy
and the dissertation so another category
theoretic work for background and the
dissertation itself
the approach is based on experiences
within the category Theory learning
group insights from The topos Institute
category Theory Outreach panel and Chang
in the joy book club
and this great line from Emily real in
her book category Theory and context in
the notes of the readers section
inevitably given the diversity of
mathematical tastes and experiences the
examples presented here will seldom be
optimized for any particular individual
and indeed each reader is encouraged to
search for their own context in which to
explore categorical ideas so this uh
curriculum is something that I'll be
living and versioning as we move forward
in the active inference applied category
space super exciting so thanks again Jr
for the Epic contribution and we all
reviewed the syllabus and just found so
many interesting aspects to it so
there's a lot to learn
no surprises there but it's awesome when
other adventurers
help
create spaces and ways for others to go
on their own adventures and it really
feels like in category theory that there
is a culture of that so it's really
encouraging
okay to the overview of the dissertation
itself
as stated earlier there are seven
chapters chapter one is an introduction
chapter 2 is a comprehensive review of
the concepts and results needed to
understand the mathematical
contributions
chapter 3 begins to reapproach neural
modeling and more generally the
algebraic modeling of the structure of
interacting systems
chapter 4 presents the first main result
that Bayesian updating composes
according to the categorical lens
pattern
chapter 5 introduces the corresponding
semantical categories with a new
abstract formalization of the concept of
open dynamical system
chapter 6 presents the functorial
formalization of predictive coding using
a new notion of approximate inference
Doctrine by which statistical models are
translated into dynamical systems
and chapter 7 reviews the prospects for
future work from the mathematics of the
cognitive map a program called
compositional cognitive cartography to
the composition of multi-agent systems
and ecosystems and the connections with
compositional Game Theory and other
categorical approaches to cybernetics
any overall thoughts on the seven
partite structure of the dissertation
just real quick if you
if you decide that you want to read this
and use this as your your leverage point
I would suggest that maybe you do it in
the usual chronological order but you
also will find that you can work
backwards in fact there's stuff in
chapter seven that literally points you
in that direction so you might want to
give it a like a once over
just to sort of Orient yourself and then
you should feel free to be able to go
bi-directionally
just to just a strategic prompt because
if you get bogged down and it's very
easy to get sort of caught up in the in
the minutia of this
I would just say Zuma step back and if
you can't if you if it's if it's not
registering on the first pass it might
register if you
start going a little bit backwards and
forwards instead of just one directional
great
and just to summarize some of the
primary contributions
few quotes the main contribution of this
thesis is the formalization of models of
predictive coding circuits as functorial
semantics and the associated development
and exemplification of categories of
statistical games
as well as the introduction of Bayesian
lenses and the proof that Bayesian
updates compose optically that is in
some sense like Optics
we believe our presentation of General
open dynamical systems as certain
polynomial co-algebras also to be novel
along with the concept of cilia and
their associated monoidal bicategories
we hope that this dissertation
contributes to a Renaissance of
cognitive and computational Neuroscience
through the adoption of categorical
methods we're going to be returning more
to all of these so it's going to be cool
and Ali it's all good with a video off
for internet's sake but just raise your
hand or bring your video on whatever you
would like to speak
before we take the jump
we just pulled out two small quotes
that's going to help us
leap off this Cliff to map the Gap
respect it and Beyond
so first
from page 226 this is from chapter 7.
this resemblance becomes even closer
when one considers the recent diegetic
open parenthesis diegetic
occurring within the context of the
story and able to be heard by the
characters within the story
the recent diegetic formulation of open
games in which strategies themselves can
be updated using a backwards map from
the arena of the game back into
strategies or rather strategy updates
and then
fundamentally from page 225 this is also
the idea underlying the successor
representation of the cognitive map
which says roughly that the brain's
representation of where it
is is
equivalently a representation of where
it soon expects to be
and so
how as we
bring that last foot of the six feet off
the other side of the cliff and jump
through the unknown how do we take this
immense work and update our strategies
backwards so that we can successfully
represent and disseminate ourselves
any final words before we jump into
chapter one on this topic
I just think if you're part of the
active infants community and you've been
wondering if there's been any sort of
question in your mind as to the role of
strategy in that relationship between
inference and action
um this is going to be really really
helpful in terms of maybe giving you a
better sense of
you identifying and then you carrying
out choices so I think it's um
I think it's very important to now
take the leap
okay
zero to one now we're in chapter one so
for the coming slides um Ali or Dean
please just if you'd like select one uh
bullet point feel free to read the
bullet point or give any remark and on
these coming slides we're just gonna
move through but either of you or both
of you please take the first uh pass all
right so chapter one introduction
um I'll let people read through the
slide I think
the one that we bolded here category
theory is the mathematics of pattern
composition connection and interaction I
think you can I think you can read that
um but I believe
you also have to kind of sit back and
ask yourself so what does that mean so
right away they're taking a
superordinate and they're breaking it up
into its parts and so it there again
there's this world within world within
World thing that is reinforced just in
the way that we have to try to
communicate the ideas to the readers
awesome and Ali
I guess and I also think the two
problems I've outlined uh in the first
page of chapter one and namely that each
research group has not only its own
language but also its own perspective
and these languages and perspectives are
not well connected
uh and these two issues I believe are
the uh organizing themes of the whole
dissertation and uh we see these issues
at rest time and time again uh
throughout the thesis uh so uh and
particular learning in chapter seven uh
which these issues are addressed uh
quite explicitly uh both in terms of the
work or the contribution done in this
thesis and the suggestions for future
research
uh the other point is that the language
of category theory is homo iconic and
can be used to translate constructions
between contexts so again uh right at
the beginning
this dissertation tries to put a
particular perspective in order to
address the the T the two issues just
mentioned so in this case uh Toby uses
the homo iconic property of category
Theory
to address the uh those two issues and
um or more explicitly category Theory
resolves both problems of scientific
translations
uh in this way that Concepts Express
categorically are inevitably expressed
in context and not in isolation
and secondly these contexts are
naturally interconnected as if by a
categorical web with the connections and
expressed categorically so in other
words category Theory provides probably
the ideal
toolkit to address those situations
which those issues which I believe is
not restricted only to Scientific
Endeavors so these two issues uh come up
in many other areas and outside science
as well so in that case I believe
category Theory can provide much more
General framework to address them even
in
non-scientific Fields as well
can I just sat onto what Ali just said
there real quick I agree with you 100
Ali about the toolkit and I would add
that I also believe it gives us an
opening to develop a rule kit
so that we can actually figure out how
to do that translation piece and it also
gives us a pool I like to use things
that rhyme because it's easy to remember
but the way that we collect how things
congregate what that attractor state
becomes so that we can then figure out
how things are moving in that Dynamic
situation so I think it provides a
toolkit a rule kit and a pool kit
great
all right next slide on chapter one I'll
just pick one and then either of you
please
the one that's exciting to me is we show
that the theory of predictive coding has
a clear compositional structure
that explains the bi-directional
circuitry observed in the brain so even
outside of the connection to the
empirical grounded embodied biology
the idea that a lot of the ways that in
retrospect informally we've been talking
over the last years as a field and in
The Institute about the compositionality
of models and can we just plug in the
sense States here to the action States
here can we Nest the models these ways
and the ways that we've been thinking
about the active inference cognitive
kernel like a Lego kit all of this is
realizing a level of formality
which doesn't mean inaccessibility
really quite the opposite that's just
accelerating what's possible with
predictive coding Bayesian brain active
inference free energy principle so we're
really seeing like a dawning of the
formal compositionality and to be able
to compose and to be able to construct
are going to have a relationship that we
can continue to weave in the coming
sessions
either of you want to highlight some
other piece here
I think it's really interesting because
I know that they are trying to build an
infrastructure but there are a lot of
this dissertation has to do with a
process that's actually a deconstructor
deconstructure meaning there's a lot of
pruning and sculpting that they actually
speak to if we were to talk about real
things that form and shape and give us
that sense of what's in and what's out
so yes they are building an
infrastructure but can they go but then
Toby goes along and speaks a whole bunch
about so why does this stay and why does
this not get included
I'll eat anything or we'll continue
um just real quick uh it reminds me of
Mario bunger's working causality also
Alan garfinkel's theory of explanation
uh because and particularly in
garfinkel's work
um in his book forms of the explanation
he uh provides a theory of explanation
based on uh rigorous modeling of
problems in terms of State spaces and
how we can address the context-dependent
explanations based on the contrast is
based on one hand and the relevance
based on the other so
category Theory I believe uh somehow
unifies
or in other words translates these kinds
of theories into a rigorous and coherent
framework that can be used to uh to to
formalize or rather to frame all of
these theories of explanations and
causalities
within a unified framework so that's I
believe one of its uh greatest
advantages
great
okay
anyone want to give a comment here
I'll just give a quick comment which is
and this is just a peek ahead to chapter
two we're only gonna have a few Snippets
from The Medium uh the Miso chapters the
the space between but don't we see
diagrams like this all the time in
active inference with internal external
and blanket States the particular
partition hierarchical predictive
processing Bayesian brain architectures
we see these diagrams all the time and
section 2.1 is extremely provocative
with the analysis of neural circuitry
and two other types of systems in really
establishing that the drawing
if it's informal is insufficient
to completely convey
the arguments and to really represent
the situation however if we use
the kind of string diagrams or just
diagrams more generally that category
Theory provides we really get a
graphical compositionality
that just drawing on a page though
obviously wonderful and fun does not
reach
and so we're going to be able to talk
about how these types of diagrams which
again we see all over the literature
can be enriched with this category
theoretic perspective so that we can
assess well what if I draw a line from
this one over to that one
is that valid how is that going to
change the properties and so we're going
to be able to know a lot more about that
when we understand the compositional
structure via the Bayesian lenses of
these compositional Bayesian systems
anything else to add on this slide
all right
Dean or Ali go ahead
so uh
chapter one begins with the claim that
the brain is the visual circuitry seems
to be roughly hierarchical and this
hierarchical structure is a hint of
compositionality and thus a sign that a
categorical approach may be helpful and
enlightening
on the other hand the underlying
equations of the freelian energy
principle exhibit a form of
compositionality which is used to obtain
the hierarchical models
despite the hint of compositionality the
equations of motion for these
hierarchical systems are typically
derived from scratch each time a
redundant effort that would not be
required at a compositional formalism
such as category Theory being used from
the start so this thesis supplies such a
categorical formalism and exemplifies it
with hierarchical predictive coding
under the free energy principle
category theory has a rich formal
vocabulary for precisely describing
Universal constructions and so not only
does a categorical formulation of the
free energy framework promise to clarify
the current confusions around fep but it
may be expected also to shed light on
its potential universality
just so
exciting and interesting and in terms of
the current the past present and future
status of the free energy principle and
active inference
it's an absolutely consequential
direction of work
Dean anything here
no I I know that in this in 741 which
we'll talk about later the introduction
of the of the term fuzzy and fuzzy
distributions comes up so even though
they're being precise
they're being precise of their fuzziness
as well
great like a high resolution picture of
a fuzzy jacket
laughs
onwards
so in this thesis we do not get as far
as a completely General formulation of
active inference and it goes without
saying this expression could be added to
every single thing that we read today
but in the coming videos and Beyond
we're going to discuss what this all
means
and just one more exciting piece from
this page
because active inference models and the
free energy framework more broadly are
descriptions of systems that are open to
an environment interacting with it and
therefore situated in context they are
particularly suited to a category
theoretic reformulation
so that's very exciting because we've
from
qualitative philosophical humanistic
approaches
and also from statistical numerical
formal approaches we've discussed a lot
of this openness and now we have another
entree or another vector or another
toolkit rule kit toolkit to work with
and that is just opening the space up a
lot
Ollie or Dean want to add anything here
just real quick we've talked in other
live streams we've used images of ice
cream cones and ice cream trucks and
what's in the foreground and what's in
the background what's actually the
context and what is the content and this
reinforces that idea of as as the
Observer as the one using their their
optic nerves what did you choose to put
in front and what is in behind and we
have to keep that in mind because we
shouldn't assume that everybody chooses
the way that we do so again just making
sure we understand what's being said
here in this slide is really important
thank you Ali
I guess and I still think it's really
clever to title the dissertation uh as
mathematical foundations for a
compositional account of the Bayesian
brain as opposed to active inference uh
because uh as we all know uh one of the
uh distinguishing features of active
inference Theory and what sets it apart
from other related theories such as
Bayesian brain and predictive coding
theories is the fundamental integration
of action into perception so
uh as long as this dissertation doesn't
provide a full-fledged account of this
kind of action integration I believe it
is more it would be more appropriate to
uh to term it as a compositional account
of the Bayesian brain and not
particularly active in Prints but of
course uh in chapter seven uh Toby
suggests some potential ways that this
kind of integration can potentially be
done in the future research
awesome
all right chapter one's already
foreshadowing the idea of cognitive maps
and Toby writes current models of
cognitive Maps some are expressed in a
language of approximate variational
inference we talk about that a lot some
are expressed in the language of
reinforcement learning some attempt to
combine the two
we expect that the foundations developed
here will help us unify these accounts
so how can we be reimagining Maps
cognitive Maps
aren't they all
aliodine anything else to add here
all right and
last few selections from chapter one
either of you please what's the first
take here
I'll go first our primary motivation in
writing this thesis is to lay the
groundwork for well-typed cognitive
science and computational Neuroscience
it's uh
a very interesting topic about the
implications of well typing and what
does it mean for something to be well
typed what is a programming language or
a scientific culture or a framework
that's well typed
the free energy framework
like the structurally adjacent framework
of compositional Game Theory has a
strong flavor of teleology
what is that taste like
and systems act in order to make their
predictions come true we come to this so
many times and in so many ways
in reinforcement or reward oriented
learning you have a reward function and
systems work to maximize reward whereas
in free energy as a bounding
variable or or functional on surprise
the imperative is to bound and reduce
surprise such that
expectations or preferences are realized
and so here it's expressed qualitatively
we've approached this in many different
paper discussions from a statistical
numerical formal analytical angle and
here we're approaching it from another
formal Avenue of category Theory
and
either of you have any
comments on this or want to talk about
the last piece
yeah talk quickly about scientific faith
in the programming that I did we had a
little
Axiom or expression that was uh if it
isn't history
then it's a mystery and I think that's
part of what the scientific Faith piece
is all about I mean if you have some
data if you have some way of
recording or or taking in or gaining
some sense of
that's great that's the historical part
but you still also need that Curiosity
and that that sense that there's the yet
still to be witnessed and observed and
you have to have some Faith that's
sticking around is going to be able to
provide that opportunity so
um yeah I think
I I don't know if it will I don't know
if a well-typed science will buttress
scientific faith I think sometimes the
personality
matters I think if you're the kind of
person who believes in
curiosity being resolved and wayfinding
being a really good strategy to find out
who you are and what the world's about I
think that's that's the faith piece that
um some of us just seem to carry around
whether we like it or not
awesome I'll eat anything on this slider
enclosure of chapter one
I just wanted to mention that by
well-typed cognitive science or more
generally well-typed science I believe
Toby uh somehow uh implying a kind of
a more or less a claim for disunity of
Sciences as opposed to a unified vision
of science because uh you see uh in the
unified Vision vision for science uh any
I mean every uh explanatory models and
every uh Theory uh can theoretically be
unified within an overarching
principle or overarching Theory which is
not been discovered yet but some
philosophers Advocate the position of
disunity of Sciences in other words uh
although there are some commonalities
between every scientific areas but there
are some
uh individual types or individual
Concepts if you will uh that is that
cannot be taken I mean the this
individuality can cannot be taken for
granted simply by just explaining it
away by uh proposing some unifying
principle so in this sense well-typed
science is a quite uh rigorous and
individualized notion of a scientific
Endeavor at least in my opinion but I'm
curious to know Toby's opinion
I'll just add one more comment on the
well-type in programming languages where
type safety or type soundness is being
described as a beneficial feature in
certain contexts obviously people point
to the way that a well-typed language
can prevent illegal operations or uh use
safer handling of short-term memory
working memory and overt logical errors
so it's very interesting to think about
what that means in science in terms of
not just the reproducibility of
experimentation but in terms of what
experiments and what research Avenues
are pursued overall as well as even
cognitive security so there's so many
different angles where well typing is
going to matter for the way that we
think about compositional cognitive
cartography which we're going to come to
now
chapter 7.
we skipped over a few pieces didn't we
that's how the last six months felt yes
I'll hold on the jokes for now but yeah
we skipped about 200 pages right there
that's
um that's the part that you wanna
take lightly
that's the bottom of the bathtub you
jump into chapter one and it's exciting
it's like skiing downhill and then this
vast Tundra opens of chapters two
through six which again was the last
half year for us and several others so
now let's get to chapter seven and then
the sandwich will be dissected with Toby
okay
with absolute humility and accuracy
Toby points to three prominent
shortcomings of the thesis Ali do you
want to summarize these three
shortcomings
sure uh so the first one is that the
notion of approximate inference Doctrine
should be tested with further
exemplification uh you know the words
and specifically uh with the problem of
double counting uh which is addressed in
uh chapter six
um so uh the the other one is that the
generative models that uh Toby is
considered in this dissertation are
somehow static despite uh its
application in modeling dynamical
systems uh so uh again this problem uh
is addressed I mean some suggestions for
overcoming this short shortcoming
address in this chapter specifically in
relation to Meyer's categorical theory
of dynamical systems uh and finally
although we consider lower level neural
circuit models we did not explicitly
connect our approximate inference
doctrines to these more biological
models so uh in other words it's not a
theory for modeling the whole iguana uh
it's just a particular it's just a
modeling framework uh for uh modeling a
very specific function of uh or the
cognitive function of the brain
I don't know that knowing your limits
should be considered a shortcoming
that's just philosophical me going
knowing well okay so of the three of us
I'm the one guy who's proud to say I get
it wrong 20 of the time I don't give a
rat's backside most often about
precision and Perfection I want to try
and so if somebody says well the thing
that I'm talking about here has its
limits and it's not going to solve all
the problems of the world I just think
that's being realistic and honest so
call it shortcomings I I see it as a bit
of a feature being self-aware of not
being able to do everything at once
yeah so often in papers it's apologetic
when it's actually the adjacent possible
and there's always an adjacent possible
indeed an expanding one so to make an
exponentially expansive apology rather
than pointing to the adjacent possible
and seeing what can become is just two
sides of the same coin with a third side
being the rim on that coin
7.1
structured worlds and 7.1.1 Bayesian
Sensor Fusion Ali how to use C Sensor
Fusion
uh just so Sensor Fusion
um is a situation where one has a number
of sensors which reports spatially
situated data and uh also
I mean it's a kind of a problem of
combining the local data with the global
data so uh in category Theory there is
uh an obvious choice for addressing this
particular problem namely the the notion
of sheeps which is a spatially coherent
data type
uh something like a bundle for which
local sections can always be uniquely
glued together into into a global
section as Toby described here and it
reminds me of uh the theory of um I mean
the derivation of The Duality between
fep and cmep uh in Bayesian mechanics
paper uh by deploying these Notions of
bundles so in other sense uh Chief
Theory and the related fields of Applied
topology and comology chromology allow
us to judge when it is possible to form
a consensus and quantify the
abstractions to the formation of
consensus uh
hence the consensus between fep and cmap
as done in Bayesian mechanics paper I
believe is done in the same sense of
Chief Theory as providing a possibility
for emerging such a consensus
and also missing from the current chief
theoretic understanding of Sensor Fusion
is a thorough treatment of belief and
uncertainty especially from a Bayesian
perspective
the first possible extension of the work
presented here is to extend the
statistical gains and approximate an
approximate inference doctrines and
hence the classes of model that they
Encompass to structured data types such
as sheaves
we expect that the first step will be to
consider categories of channels between
sheeps
awesome and just to give a more mundane
or empirical example of Sensor Fusion
what if we have many EEG sensors on
ahead and we need to synthesize into one
joint representation or what if we have
temperature sensors across an
agricultural field and humidity Sensors
how this happens is called Sensor Fusion
and category theory is helping us
understand the compositionality of such
issues Dean
yeah can I I just want to focus in on
bullet number two here because
Daniel I think both both you and Ali I
think you're absolutely correct I think
where they say something like a bundle
for which local sections can always be
uniquely glued together into a global
section
well of course they can
but I don't know that that's necessarily
the magic what if what if in a counter
factual sense what if they are glued
does that some is that something we must
commit to
um
and then if it is going to be glued
together into some sort of global
um composition
um when
that that timing of when to do that I
also think is is is something that we
judge
uh so is that the data set the what if
and the and the when is that the data
set that we're going to eventually bump
into I would argue yes
does that mean we're going to have to
pass through that moment and come out on
the other side of it hopefully still
intact yes
to me that is consensus building
so I know that that's one little
sentence in a 200 page paper but again
there are so many nuggets in this paper
where if you just slow down and read it
and think about what the implications of
what they're saying are you could
literally go up right there on that one
sentence and spend hours trying to
figure out okay so so really what should
we be doing with this is this a priority
whatever
awesome
continuing on
uh to address that first shortcoming
we already mentioned sheaves and we hope
that these tools will suggest new
connections to work on Quantum theoretic
formulations of the free energy
framework that's something we've
discussed in several streams series live
stream 17 with Chris fields on
information flow in context dependent
hierarchical Bayesian inference live
stream 40 with friston Levin glazebrook
and Fields
on a free energy principle for generic
Quantum systems and the ongoing Chris
Fields course physics as information
processing 2023 so category Theory and
adjacent tools are already widely
utilized in Quantum Sciences Quantum
information science more broadly Quantum
computation and so on one hand we see
the quantum and free energy principle
synthesis outlined in these streams
series and here we have the category
Theory active inference Bayesian brain
free energy principle synthesis so all
three category Theory Quantum and fep
walk into a Sheaf
what do they say
all right Ali what is a uh summary or
overview on learning structure and
structured learning
oh
yeah uh yes so an interesting
distinction is provided right at the
beginning between structured learning
and learning structure so structured
learning uh at least Toby means
extending the process of learning to a
structured setting but by learning
structure he means learning the
underlying structures themselves
uh so in the categorical semantics of
dependent type Theory the context is
witnessed by the object over which a
slice category is defined and in so in
some sense it defines the shape of the
universe
construction there is correspondence
between sheaves and certain bundles as
objects of slice categories and so we
can think of structured inference and
learning as taking place in appropriate
slice categories so both of those uh
somehow address uh the the binary
concepts of structure learning and
learning the structure in a
complementary way
uh so we can think of bundle morphisms
as generalized parameters maps and in
that case the problem of learning
structure then becomes a problem of
generalized parameter learning
and this is uh the way that some
reinforcement learning uh techniques
have been deployed by using uh this kind
of generalized parameter learning so we
expect this line of inquiry to clarify
the relationships between our formalism
of approximate inference and other
related work on the categorical
foundations of cybernetics which have
typically been studied in a differential
rather than probabilistic setting
we expect the connection to be made by
information geometry where Bayesian
inference can be understood both using
gradient descent and as a kind of
parallel transport in other words it is
a way to unify both the physical
formulation of a physical formulation of
a system as done through the
differential equations in cybernetics
and also the probabilistic formulation
of the systems as done in Bayesian
mechanics
awesome just two quick notes on this
first the growth and deak construction
Shawna Dobson spoke about this in the
math art guest stream
in the context of
the evolution of Art and other areas in
math and philosophy over the last
hundred years with this Progressive
swarmification Chief vacation of self so
that's really cool to see
um
and then we expect the connection to be
made
what we expect is what we prefer and
then what we expect slash prefer is
shaping our action selection to realize
it so again once we as mentioned earlier
understand that systems act in order to
make their expectations realized we see
that these kinds of expressions are more
than just the expression of a belief
they're also in some ways an action
imperative
Dean any thoughts oh I could go for days
on this section of course because but I
will say this who knew there was so much
to be loaded up between the difference
of a verb tense right structure and
structure and add a d and all of a
sudden we're discretized between process
and product
I'll just start there and wait for Toby
to come on because I gotta I could
literally have a field date I'm at the
circus the carnival and
every single theme park in the world
when it comes to this stuff so
it's it's awesome all right
now we get two
seven one three compositional cognitive
cartography sailing the three C's Ali
what is this section about
okay so uh this is mainly uh
uh addresses the success of
representation and uh I mean doing a
kind of a comparison between a
successive representation and other uh
cognitive math theories uh in other
words the topos theoretic developments
sketched so far May provide a suitable
setting in which to understand the
neural basis for navigation and help
explain how ostensibly spatial
navigation processes and circuits are
invariably involved in more abstract
problem solving
atopus is not only a rich richly
structured category of spaces or spatial
types but it can also be understood as a
category as a category category by the
space itself
but an important notion here is that
under the free energy principle there's
a close relationship between beliefs
about the geometry of an environment and
beliefs about expected future
trajectories in that environment so this
is basically the idea behind success
representation of the cognitive map
which says roughly that the brain's
representation of where it is is
equivalently a representation of where
it soon expects to be so under the free
energy principle and similarly under the
successor representation the expected
Dynamics is a geodesic flow which is
determined by beliefs about the spatial
geometry
uh but uh crucially these beliefs are
not aesthetic they depend on what the
agent believes
will happen and this has been suggested
as an explanation or the predictive
nature of the cognitive map in other
words if we
don't take into consideration the
uncertainty behind the information about
available to the agent then we wouldn't
get to formalize the behavior in a truly
predictive way because obviously there
isn't any uncertainty to predict about
and then compare the prediction with the
actual data the cognitive map has its
essential Locus in the hippocampus which
we may therefore understand as
representing the base space over which
the big topos is sliced and since change
the plan seemed therefore to induce
changes of Base we might see the
functional connectivity of the brain as
witnessing as witnessing this
mathematical structure and this
particular claim I believe is
Perhaps Perhaps perfectly unto uh
Jackie's theory of brain from inside out
so bujaki
provides a kind of theory that
sets the hippocampus as a kind of the
agential
center of uh of all the cognitive tasks
that meet that needs to be
reconstructed from inside out as opposed
to just processing the coming data in a
kind of purely computational
unidirectional way
we talked a lot about and certainly will
in the coming weeks about what is
witnessing
how is witness related to observation
but we'll come back to that
okay continuing on on the compositional
cognitive cartography
there's some discussion about the
internal universe of the topos
not just the topos Institute but the
concept
and the way that the representations of
the cognitive map are inherently context
dependent therefore it fits naturally
within the subjectivist metaphysics
implied by the free energy framework a
topic that I know Ali is extremely
interested in
and dinar Ali any other comments on this
slice
maybe we can start calling them slice or
a bundle instead of a slide
well if we go if we do go the slice root
one thing I I would just pause for a
second
um
I think for most people in in context
geometry or geometric stability
is usually the association whereas
geodesic flow which was mentioned in the
last slide is a lot more Dynamic and I
think
that if we're going to talk about a
composition like the the flow of the of
the of the piece of music that's now
playing out we have to think of this as
both framed and filtered and so these
sheaves allow for that that sense of
distribution that that movement part
um
I think metaphorically of of exploit
exploitation and exploration now being
the two passengers in the HOV lane and
HOV lanes in North America at least are
designated by a diamond so you can see
how the geometry and the geodesic again
can all be put together and you're
starting to build a picture in in these
different
in these different models and maps that
you may be constructing
great
7.2
societies of systems
I'll just say that a collection of
purely passive agents is no Society at
all
what would it even be
Ali want to add anything more on the
forwards and backwards perhaps in the
compositional structure
uh well first of all I wanted to just
point uh that
the the very first sentence here
recollection purely passive agents is no
Society also applies to one of my
favorite
metaphysical theories out there namely
the assemblage Theory so we can say that
a collection of purely passive agents is
now assemblage as well but in any case
the doctrines of approximate inference
introduced in this thesis are inherently
perceptual
uh but the forwards channel of a
statistical gain points towards the
environment predicting the expected
incoming sense data whereas the
backwards Channel points from the
environment into the agent terminating
in the agents most costly abstract
beliefs one way in which we can
incorporate action and their Pi thereby
shape the framework of this thesis into
a framework for active imprints the
forwards channel should predict not only
sense data incoming from the environment
but also the actions to be taken by the
agent so up until now in the
dissertation
he has provided
in quite
um I mean with elaborate detail how uh
this kind of
um formulation of the bi-directional
channels can be used to reframe uh the
perceptual side of active inference but
as I mentioned earlier uh he doesn't go
so far as to integrate the action into
this framework as well but of course
here is a potential Way Forward
which can which we can deploy the same
forwards Channel as being the actions to
be taken by the environment because of
the same directionality uh it possesses
we therefore expect the compositional
theory of active inference to have
forwards Channel rather so so that an
agent sensorium depends on the
configuration or quote-unquote action
that it has chosen
and another uh very in my opinion
significant Point here is the
substitution of the notion of markup
blankets throughout the whole
dissertation uh with the notion of
polynomial functors uh because uh as
have been discussed in uh the previous
chapters as well markup blankets doesn't
provide a rigorous enough uh concept to
be applied uh quite at least directly in
category Theory so polynomial functors
substitute the well-known notional
markup blanket as used in active
inference literature to characterize uh
the basically the same thing or the
interaction boundaries of adaptive
agents
yes so many great pieces here Marco
blanket used in the informal active
inference literature
like everything we've been studying for
the last few years all of that
casual light Airy Breezy we had fun now
it's time to formalize that
um and and there's so much more we can
say about backwards and forwards but
we'll just um Carry On
foreign
active inference
there are some mentions about the
resemblance between active inference and
economic games in terms of
their both having lenses into the area
or the arena of interaction and this
line of inquiry naturally leads on to
the consideration of multi-agent systems
perhaps this can be investigated with
poly algebras
7.2.2 what is the type of a plan
perception and action are thus in
general the tool two dual ways in which
a system can minimize its free energy
change your mind change the world
akin to the two degrees of freedom
available in an auto encoder game
discussed in the thesis
A system that acts
must necessarily be motivated towards
some goal and in order to realize its
goal the system must enact a plan
Dean pick it up from here
uh
well I will just say this I'm not going
to speak to this stuff on the slide
necessarily at the very end of this
section he somebody writes this promises
to ask what is the form of this data and
how can we incorporate it into the
compositional framework in other words
what is the type of a plan
these seem to us to be key questions for
future work this prompted me to go and
then we wonder why teachers struggle
sometimes to necessarily remember what
it was like to be the learner
because we can come up with a plan
because we've done the learning we're
now the learn ad right
the the learner now changes because of
one cup
sorry tense
present to past tense change and or why
the plan that we put before Learners
removes all the critical work for
self-organizing this is the cost of
being a teacher because if we do the
planning force of it and I understand
why we have to do it because if they're
walking into a space we don't want them
falling off jumping off cliffs
necessarily and not having you know a
soft Landing however
um
we do need to talk a little bit about
what is the type of a plan and what are
the benefits and the costs of choosing
to use that strategy going forward
especially if we're in the role of
somebody who's supposed to be guiding
opening up worlds Horizons and all that
other stuff
thank you ollie any other comments on
this section
not at the moment
one piece to me is it seems
unnecessarily crude to hide all of this
data
which is described as a lot of data
inside of a single undifferentiated
choice of Prior distributions
so that's very interesting in light of
again the statistical numerical
quantitative way that we've approached
policy selection as inference planning
as inference action and inference
what does it mean to differentiate this
choice
okay
reinforcement learning open games and
ecosystems Ali any summary here
okay so
um
as also indicated in the first sentence
uh there was a close relationship
between active and Theory markup
decision problems and reinforcement
learning as uh explored numerous times
before and uh many paper but uh the
standard algorithm for
gaining an optimality for policy
selection is usually called backward
induction in reinforcement learning or
akas dynamic programming so namely
backward induction is structured
according to a similar bi-directional
pattern or the optic pattern to that of
both Bayesian inference and reverse
differentiation that Mt mdps themselves
fit into the associated general
framework of open games
so in the informal active inference
approach to mdps the system in question
counterfactually evaluates policies
using a backward induction-like process
accumulating free energies in order to
score them
now in this process that it is this
process that results in the prior uh
that we're uh we're all familiar with uh
in active inference context which is
then updated by the agent's inference
process but uh future work will need to
untangle this amount of interrelated uh
bi-directional process in other words
how we can uh
explicitly determine in what way uh
those um those kinds of project
processes although being quite in a
quite different with having with quite I
mean opposite directionality can be
unified into
um into a unified framework so we hope
that having done so we will show how the
whole picture emerges and how it relates
to the developing geometric or diegetic
framework in category Oracle cybernetics
possibly involving the further
development of our notion of cilia
great
continuing on with reinforcement
learning open games and ecosystems since
the free energy principle underlying
active inference asserts a certain
informal universality
we might also hope that the satisfactory
development of compositional active
inference might exhibit a universal
property
that any other doctrine of cybernetic
systems
factors uniquely through it
there's some discussion of multi-agent
systems
and their implied Global search
casting this account into the emerging
framework of compositional active
inference will Point towards a bridge
to multi-agent reinforcement learning
the resulting General accounts of
multi-agent intelligence
will Encompass both reinforcement
learning and active inference allowing
us to understand their relative
strengths and difference
we hope that one distal outcome of the
work will be a new and beneficial
understanding of corporate activity
sometimes called organizational
cybernetics
or meta governance
we should expect any framework resulting
from this work to capture existing
models of collective active inference
such as recent work on spin glasses or
ant colonies
any other thoughts on this yes Dean
I I know that this is my bias is
literally on the surface but I believe
that the idea of open games and opened
will be ened ecosystems is
a future path that a lot of formalized
and structured learning is going to take
it's it's the work that I did
essentially for
for 10 years and so I think that
everything that you're seeing here may
become one a new model that can be
optioned into in terms of how you would
want to structure your learning so this
is I think this is really important
stuff
how you'd like to structure your
learning and how you'd like to learn
structure exactly
7.3 the mathematics of life
we move on to consider the relationships
between compositional active inference
and the Contemporary mathematics of life
we hope that compositional active
inference May Supply part of the story
of a modern theory of autopiliesis the
ability for life to recreate itself
so just some brief notes on topics that
are near and dear to us as we get close
to the end
7.3.1 Bayesian mechanics and the free
energy principle
recently it has been suggested in
various venues citation 53 and 54.
Carl friston 2019 a free energy
principle for a particular physics
and Fort 54. par DeCosta and friston
Marco blankets information geometry and
stochastic thermodynamics
that the free energy framework provides
a universal way to understand the
behavior of adaptive systems
Bayesian mechanics promises to build
upon the nascent understanding of random
Dynamics via inference
245.
Dalton's octivitaville towards a
geometry and Analysis for Bayesian
mechanics and ramstead at all on
Bayesian mechanics a physics of and by
beliefs also check out live stream
number 49.
to supply a new theory of Mechanics for
statistical systems the present
formulation of Bayesian mechanics is
constructed using mathematical tools
from physics
but not
yet
the kinds of compositional tools
promoted in this thesis
we expect that developments along the
lines sketched here will unify the
ongoing developments of Bayesian
mechanics with the new synthetic
understanding of mathematical physics by
casting all Dynamics as abstract
inference we should also expect this
line of inquiry to begin to quantify the
Persistence of things
and imbue much of physics within Elon
vital
with a vital energy
any thoughts on this
okay well I was just going to say that I
think that section there's a you've
already talked about the importance of
adjunction and I this section literally
makes that very very clear I think that
the relation and the translation
are kind of the on and through of this
this part of where the amazing mechanics
and the free energy principle help us
understand
that there's a statistical game that's
also strategic
so again I'll be interested to talk to
Toby about that
great carrying on with mathematics life
732 biome biosemiotics Ali want to give
any summary or thoughts on biosemiotics
sure so
um the emerging biosemiotic
reconceptualization of Life explicitly
acknowledges the importance in
universality of communication in context
proposing that in
in any such situation the interpreting
system necessarily has an internal
representation of the external world
so to speak it's unwell which is updated
by interpreting incoming signals we can
in principle reconstruct the external
World by understanding it as that which
a collection of systems agrees about
perhaps then the shared Universe has
determined topus theoretically the
fusion of active inference agents is a
good model of this semiosphere
it seems therefore that mathematics
resulting from our work on internal
universes and their interactions and
more broadly many of the formal
ingredients of compositional active
inference is well aligned with the
informal structures of biosemiotics and
so it may be desirable to re-express
biosemiotics accordingly in doing so
perhaps the mathematics of a modern
Bayesian subjectivist metaphysics will
be found for instance by expressing
communication and its phenomenology as a
geometric morphism a generalized base
change between agents internal universes
and it might be worth mentioning here
the work of people like Terence Deacon
and also
Karen bronze agential realism because
I mean in Terence Deacon's work and
particularly in his book and called
incomplete nature he provides a kind of
nested hierarchy of how
how various kinds of informations as
provided to biological organisms are
structured in a nested hierarchical way
that would allow the agent to
distinguish the
purely informational data as opposed to
the semantic data that is in the
innermost level of the nested hierarchy
and also
Karen broad's agential realism provides
this notion of intraction which allow
allow the
the agent or the system of interest to
co-constitute itself via the very
interaction with the environment so it's
not just pure interaction between the
system and its environment but rather
both the agent and the environment
co-constitutes themselves through the
intra action so it might be
worth exploring some of these ideas with
Toby as well
Dean anything to add on this one
no I think Ali summed it up perfectly
all right and the final section
fundamental Theory
future work connected to this thesis
need not only be an application
a number of purely theoretical questions
raise themselves to so for people who we
could already hear in the live chat in
the YouTube comments complaining that
this was too practical to application
oriented don't worry there's also some
theoretical questions that raise
themselves so first geometric methods
for structured belief updating
the mathematics of belief is in large
part about replacing definite points
with fuzzier distributions over them in
fact this PDF copy error
with a fuzzy interpretive system allows
the word to be read by a human
independent type Theory we replace
points with terms
non-dependent terms are exactly points
so a type Theory with belief should
somehow Encompass fuzzy terms
we might well want to express beliefs
about things whose identity we are not
quite sure
742 Dynamics
chapter 5 supplies the beginnings of a
compositional co-algebraic theory for
open stochastic and random dynamical
systems in general time
and we hope that this Theory could
provide a home for a modern account of
non-equilibrium systems home home on the
state space
and 743 computation
a new understanding of computation may
follow the semiotic understanding of
information processing that we propose
above
perhaps we could say more precisely that
computation is the Dynamics of semiosis
the time is right for such a
reconceptualization as human-made
systems increasingly move away from Von
Neumann architectures towards more
biosimilar ones such as memristers
Optical processors neuromorphic
technology graph processors or even many
core and mesh based evolutions of
classical processors so some absolutely
fantastic theoretical Avenues to pursue
any of you want to comment on some of
these Avenues Dean please
in the dynamic section
um
there's a really really interesting
again more confirmation bias in my world
um
he says here chapter five is supplied
beginnings of the composition of
co-algebraic theory for open stochastic
and random dynamical systems in general
time
me being a Time guy that's cool and we
hope that this Theory could provide a
home for for a modern account of
non-equilibrium systems with category
polynomial functions applying a
satisfactory account of these systems
and then I'm going to slow down because
this is the part that I really like
interfaces in Brackets I.E the
boundaries across which information
flows along and in the word along
there's the word on in the middle
which they compose
and through which they interact and me
being an on and through it being the
same thing this was fantastic
confirmation of that in in a dynamic
sense
and Ali
uh yes and um
uh also again I think uh some of the
work
um done by Bob Coke and his colleagues
regarding the uh Bayesian
Basin Quantum inference and especially
uh I mean
proposing a kind of string diagrams uh
in the sense of uh I mean used in
category Theory to explore the whole
theory of uh the quantum Bayesian
inference uh I believe it it maps onto
this sense of Dynamics as provided by
Toby in the final pages of his
dissertation uh in the case that uh in
the basic Quantum inference it is also a
question of how to provide the exact
time evolution of each state or each
agent not uh strictly in a linear sense
but both uh in linear and in sorry in
the predictive and also the retroactive
sense in other words by taking into
account the whole Arrow of time not just
a particular instant uh or a particular
moment of it so
in this in the sense I think the
discussion of non-equilibrium systems
which is still an underexplored area of
physics uh can uh by using a category
Theory can help to unify or at least
make connections between these kinds of
predictive models as used in classical
physics and also some of the retroactive
models as recently proposed in Quantum
Bayesian theorem
great
and so
we couldn't escape
without showing at least a little bit of
a hint
of what realistically much of the
dissertation looks like
so next time we're gonna jump into the
thick of it these kinds of equations and
diagrams are what you're going to find
when you unpack the dissertation and of
course there's so much to add and we did
so much work on just scratching the
surface of what these diagrams are and
how they actually convey formality in
category Theory
and uh
it's gonna be great to work and talk
together on them and with Toby
um
where does that leave us fellows Dean
with the uh pre-pen ultimate thought and
then Ali
well I think that there's going to be a
big shift from the this this today's
live stream which
um
guys to be gentle on on us but also
anybody who's really curious as to where
this goes next I think it's going to get
a it's going to get a lot more um
it's going to be a lot more
sophisticated and there's going to be a
little bit more um
work to do but I think I think at least
we've we've started out a path that it
hopefully we've piqued your curiosity as
the last question says what are you
still curious about I think there's I
think there's a lot coming up that um
should be pretty good for those that
want to really get dig dig down into the
real formalisms and the real structure
of this
thank you Dean Ali
uh well yeah at the end of our six month
uh joyful ride through this dissertation
uh I believe
uh at least uh from from a personal
Performance Point of View
I've truly learned a lot and uh it
piqued my interest in lots of domains
and areas which I didn't know I have
interest in them before
so uh I I think it's a really uh a good
Mark of an influential work uh be it a
dissertation or a book or paper or any
other kinds of academic publication uh
to Peak people's mind to explore in uh
even unexplored some unexplored areas
and try to
connect the dots in a very
I mean in particular in the category
Theory sense in a very rigorous
well-typed and uh
even insightful ways and uh maybe some
exciting developments and results uh can
be can emerge from these times kinds of
dark connections
thank you both for this excellent stream
I have so much gratitude for the whole
category Theory team not just the
sheaves around Toby that enable and
scaffold this work but also the way that
we were able to collaborate
over the last months and
in the bigger picture
maybe the end of a chapter we just
finished chapter one
which or chapter zero and that's really
what the dot zero is so we were in the
dot double o
now we are bringing the dot zero to a
closure soon we're gonna jump into the
dot one and the dot two with Toby and
even that in some other nested scale is
a double o or a DOT zero so thank you
again Ali and Dean at all
till next time
thank you bye